If you want to ship more and build faster, you have to create a founder-like agency inside your company. A single engineer can do what two teams of engineers could do two years ago. Suddenly, the market opportunity landscape is just much broader and you can do more with software. How do you guys ship so much product? Companies have skewed in that direction where they've seen this new agentic efficiency and power as a way to optimize cost structure. Our
Belief, I'm being a little cheeky, but build everything. Yes, the Opus 4.5 Cambrian explosion moment. We haven't had that in agent to commerce today. And there's a few reasons for that. One is we are merging so much more code than last year and is stressing every system. So we create something called Stripe Minions. You're not going to iterate, not go into planning mode. You're just going to say, this is what I want. Go do it. That's kind of where the world is going. You guys are, I think, over two trillion of volume now.
What do you think is sort of the future state of how we all access models and tokens? And very bullish on... AI is making engineers dramatically more productive. Stripe's response isn't to build the same things with fewer people. It's to build more. In this episode, A16Z General Partner David George sits down with Stripe's Will Gabrik to unpack how AI is changing the way one of the world's largest technology companies builds. They discuss Stripe's internal coding agents.
which recently generated 7,000 pull requests in a single week. Why teams are becoming smaller and flatter, and how Stripe is trying to give engineers the kind of agency traditionally associated with founders. Then they look at what all this new software means for commerce itself. From AI agents sparring software from other agents, to micro payments, stable coins, and why Will believes the checkout page will eventually disappear altogether. I want to start with
Just a state of strike. Yes. So what is striped today and when we originally invested it payment processor But now I think the average AI company uses 11 different strike products and at sessions I believe you had 288 distinct Mm-hmm product launches. So I want to talk about velocity also But just to start with just what is the state of strike today? So internally
we think about Stripe as having inverted our value proposition from being a payments company with sort of add-ons. So now being this multi-product platform where everything sort of focuses on financial infrastructure, helping you grow by reducing the friction and increasing the agency to be more agile with your business model, to operate in more countries and just go faster when it comes to everything that touches revenue and cash.
So just practically speaking went from payments to then billing subscriptions and invoicing connect if you're a platform or marketplace radar for me digging fraud Radar now for doing many more things than that tax just I think we don't actually count but somewhere in and around 25 30 products that are sort of headlining branded products and then of course hundreds and thousands of features below that But again the framework we think about is really
Reducing frictions and increasing agency. So a good example last year We saw a lot of users for the first time experiencing free trial abuse and this wasn't really an issue pre AI because Most grape users are software companies. Yeah margins. Yeah, exactly burden wasn't there yet. So they're wasting a little compute. Yeah, it's negligible. It's de minimis But now software as a cost structure and so actually I think cursor was the first
user that was gonna say it was our portfolio. Yes, exactly. Experienced it. I guess internet users can be crafty, but yes. Yes, yes, and I think it was something like one in six users of free trials were abusive and so you're just throwing money at these users who are just signing up for another account, another account, another account, maybe even doing model distillation and things like that. And so we sort of got in the bunker with them
and just stood up in a weekend a pipeline where we were able to use our foundation model, look across the entire Stripe network, use our embeddings, and then after that put a reasoning layer on top of it so you could sort of say, we think this is a free trial abuser because and point to those signals. And I think it's today, I think it's 11 labs recently told us that they're blocking 2000 free trial abusers.
per day using stripe signals. Incredible. So you just think about how much money you'd be burning if you were, well how much money you wouldn't, how much revenue you wouldn't be creating if you weren't getting these trials. Yeah, exactly. Yeah, the false positives and the false, yeah, exactly. Exactly. And then on the increasing agency side, it's still just so hard to go global. You have to go out having to register, calculate, remit taxes in so many geographies. And this new crop of AI companies, the digital goods companies, and they want to just go global very fast.
And so, I guess, ARIFS is a good example. They're using this product stripe managed payments where in their home markets, the US, let's say they have an entity in Europe, they are the seller of record, but in long-tail markets, you know, the Kazakh sands and all over APAC where they haven't sort of entities, stripe stands in as the actual merchant of record, we handle all tax calculation, tax remittance and everything like that. And so let's just let some cover 100 plus geographies.
and complying with me. Yeah, that's amazing. Yeah. And if you go back to the fraud example, if you identify abusive actors, there's actually a network effect in that business, right? Which is super powerful. And obviously we appreciate it as investors in many of the companies who benefit from it. So if you look at the product set today, obviously the origin of Stripe was startups. And so you can very easily stand up payments, sell stuff online, and then famously,
Part of the beauty of Stripe's growth and business model is that you captured companies like DoorDash and Instacart when they were in YC. And then you grew with them along the way. How do you think about the product strategy as it relates to serving startups versus serving large enterprises now? So I think it was actually Colin at clerk who summarized our strategy nicely on next recently where he said
Stripe strategy is unabashed and paraphrasing his words, but it's win all the startups and then win them again. And I think to some extent that's just a good business model because startups are very ambitious. They typically grow into the biggest companies of tomorrow. They're sort of canaries for what the next opportunity is. So another subtle reason to win all the startups and win them again is they actually have the highest standards of all of our customers.
I looked recently at the CSAP for Stripes Reporting and for our very, very large enterprise users, your reporting is great. We love the data you give us. It's way better than anything we get from any of our other customers. Because they're accustomed to the incumbents. Exactly. And then you look at it for startups, your reporting is garbage. You have got to fix this. This is driving me crazy. And so there's this persistent sense that startups just make us better by being the fastest, by being the most demanding and so on. But of course, once we start working with startups, we want to work with them forever.
And so this pulls us up market and forces us to become as sort of surprisingly great. That's the standard we try to hold ourselves to for enterprises as for startups. And now we're working with I don't know the exact percentages today, but it's not quite half, but we're getting there. 4,500 companies. We work, of course, with the Amazon, the world, Microsoft's and at the enterprise, it's sort of a different sales cycle. It's a different post-sale activation motion. It's a lot more required.
after you've already signed the contract, where it started to go live like that. But fundamentally, it's the same thing. You just stay close to the user, you hear their needs, you show that you're sort of provably better when it comes to the metrics they care about. And yeah, so it's really both at this stage. Yeah, win them and then win them again. I love that. That's a great dynamic. I want to shift gears. So I think you guys publicly said that first half signups grew 50% year over year. And that the median 26 cohort
is generating 50% more revenue than the comparable 25 cohort. So, and then I think the 25 cohort was generating 70% more revenue than the comparable 24 cohort. So what has changed? Yeah. Well, I think two things. One is, is giving rise to so much opportunity for new business creation. There's just things you couldn't do before that you could do now. You couldn't build a Suno.
four years ago, or you could maybe build a much worse Suno four years ago. You couldn't build a Higgs field four years ago. There's just new things that you can do. And so suddenly the market opportunity landscape is just much broader and you can do more with software. On the other side, the sort of cost of doing more software has decreased a lot because you just need many fewer engineers to build the things that you want to build because of, you know, agentic coding.
And so we're just seeing this explosion in new software creation. When you look at the, you're on your increase in usage of Stripe billing, it's actually a lot higher than usage of Stripe overall, because it disproportionately skews towards people creating software companies. Yeah, yeah. Oh, that's fantastic. That's awesome to hear. I want to shift now to some of the products that we talked about, right? So you have this proliferation of new products to serve.
all the needs of companies online. The high-level question is like, how do you do that? Like, how do you guys ship so much product? Yeah. Well, speed has always been near the top. Maybe user, relentless focus on users by the top. Yeah, of course. Yeah. Exactly. But speed is right up there. And it's interesting. I think a lot about institutional progress. And we study
the great companies that have come before us and now are beside us, the Amazons are still around of course. But you look at Stripe and you'd say, okay, well, we have sort of adapted version of how we set goals that's quite similar to Google's OKRs. Our sales team is organized pretty similarly to Microsoft's. We have a DRI culture similar to Apple's and we have a...
product quality standard and how we do our product reviews is similar to theirs. A lot of the day-to-day mechanisms that I use to sort of run the business, I've basically stolen from Alan Malali, the former CEO of Ford and Boeing Aviation. And so we study these companies and we try to bring it all into Stripe. And we think about just how do we create an enduring institution that can sort of outlast any of us because it's a great container for entrepreneurship.
And then you sort of reach today and there's just no one to copy. What do you do when a single engineer can do what two teams of engineers could do two years ago? And sort of the theory of mind right now is that Stripe needs to become more than it ever has been before a platform for founders internally.
And it's always been a platform for founders externally. Yeah, yeah, of course. The customers, yeah. Exactly. And founders have always done incredibly well at Stripe. You know, we actually was an increasing company, Metronome. Yeah, of course. We acquired Metronome last year and Scott Woody, the CEO, is thriving at Stripe. He's leading. Yeah. Leading all of Metronome and billing at this point. We acquired Privy, which is a...
while it's infrastructure company and bridge over the last couple of years. And Henry is now leading most of crypto. Zach is leading open USD and bridge. Of course, Asta from PrimPripy is leading up engineering for crypto. JR Far from lemon squeezy is leading to Treasury at this point. And so just founders have always done very well at Stripe. But now you have this very interesting moment where senior engineers are just so powerful. Yes. And so you say, well,
there's a few different ways our work could be shaped going forward. It could be that we just have many fewer engineers and maybe that's what the world would look like. I think a lot of companies have skewed in that direction where they've seen this new, you know, agentic efficiency and power as a way to optimize cost structure. You saw some layoffs, you saw, you know, companies ranking up X and our
belief is that it's just an opportunity to and being a little cheeky but build everything. Yes, yeah, and you know the best way to optimize your cost structure is to grow more. Yes, exactly. We have reams of user asks going back many years that are unmet and so we just want to get through them all faster. And so while we have you know more and more productivity from those senior engineers, if you want to ship more and build faster you have to create founder-like agency.
inside your company. And so the main things that are holding back our progress today are actually sort of back office things. You know, we are merging so much more code than last year and it is stressing every system. It is stressing how do we get things into our seller systems? How do we get things onto our pricing page? How do I actually bring things to market when we can't train sellers on them fast enough? And so we are really trying at this stage to optimize every single phase of
We think of it as the critical path in Stripe from the ideas behind product development the user asks all the way to products being in user's hands. And so to your question of how do you go faster, it's really two things. It's one, just how do you create that agency for everyone at Stripe? How do you let everyone at Stripe be an auteur, like a founder, a creative?
and not have them held back by the morass of centralized processes. Exactly. And on the other side then, it's how do you, with your Dev prod team, just make the tools better and better and better. So we create something called Stripe Minions, which we've blogged about a little bit. And of course we've got tons of developer tooling to help users iterate with agents. But Minions we think of as
you know, the most important, like one of our most important metrics internally is how many PRs and what percentage of our PRs are created by minions. And the reason for that is that minions are one shot. Yeah. So you give it a prompt and you know, it's going to build it and then it's going to, you know, go through CI CD and all of testing and then you're going to review it. So if you're not going to iterate, not going to planning mode, you're just going to say, this is what I want. Go do it.
And so we think, you know, that's kind of where the world is going. You know, it's the one shot or the glorified Ralph loop where you're just letting the agent be super, super powerful. And so we blogged about minions, I think in January, February, and they were doing 1200 PRs per week. And last week, I think 7,000 PRs came from minions. Wow. Yeah. And about 30% of our PRs in that week came from minions. So, you know, that sort of
develop for tooling and then the internal processes just get out of the way and make the tools amazing and that's how we're gonna go fast. That's amazing. In terms of empowering senior engineers who are now more powerful than ever, have you made any dramatic changes to how you organize the company internally? So obviously the minions example is incredible and I assume the 30% is gonna go to a very high percentage within a year or something.
But some of the things that we've heard from other companies is taking your most powerful engineers, putting them into business units or closer to the customers. But then you have sort of coordination problems that come from that. So like how have you guys approached that empowerment? So engineers have always been some of the most important product leaders at Stripe. We build for engineers, for technical users. Of course we've built for many personas at this point, but engineers have always been sort of the hero, ICP.
for Stripe. And so because of that engineers have always been some combination of engineer, PM, designer. And so I think we're just leaning even more into that. You know, we're building tools and platforms so that engineers can sort of do a lot of the front-end development themselves and front-end design themselves. Probably, you know, just the shortest answer to your question is flatter.
Yeah, flatter. Smaller teams. Smaller teams, flatter. You had a lot of layers that were orchestrating work and very valuably so. Right, at this time. Exactly. But you just don't need that anymore. I was talking to one of our most senior engineers recently. In fact, the guy who built Strait Projects, because Strait Projects was basically a PM and a very senior engineer and a few weeks. And a couple of other engineers who
jumped in as well. So I want to give them due credit. But most of the PRs came from one guy. It's got Alexander. Now he's just got a screen. He's orchestrating 16 agents and he's going a whole lot faster. Yeah, that's amazing. Do you have a standard team size for projects like this? Is it like we've gone around it's like, okay, one, you know, one, there's no social dynamic and so maybe that doesn't work. And you know, four is probably the max size and we've heard everything in between. Yeah. If you want it. Not really. I mean, we still have
I mean, you kind of want, in a Flutter org, you both want wider teams, right? Because that means fewer layers of management. But then, you know, you also sort of believe you can have fewer people because each individual is more empowered these days. And so I think those forces are offsetting to some extent today. And in fact, it's more like, you know, if you have a line managed team of eight people,
They're just doing 3x more. Yeah, exactly. You might have the same manager to the manager to IC ratio, but the team is doing three things rather than one. Yeah, that makes total sense. So one of the things that you know, I have talked about is and you touched on it, but I'd like to expand on a little more is this idea that you can do all these new things with AI and so where do you direct the efforts? And so you guys have very clearly directed the efforts toward
the front-facing stuff, so building new products for customers. And lots of what is discussed in the market is back-in-facing stuff. So optimizing your call structure, as you said, everything is a markdown file, and let's map out everything that everyone does in the organization and optimize it to death. Talk about your philosophy for why you want to go for the former and not the latter. Yeah. So I think there was an early narrative, and it still lingers for sure. And there's some truth to it.
of just we have agents now, we should be more efficient, we should be able to do more with less. And the main thing I actually think about on this front is making our people more productive. We have a tool internally called CHI, which is our knowledge AI tool. And we built it maybe six months ago, two people built it.
Now 83% daily active, or sorry, 80% weekly active, about 60% daily active at Stripe.
Seller productivity is increased by 20%. But we're not saying, wow, we need fewer sellers. We're saying, so we need a lot more sellers. The idea of payback of our sellers just got way better. We have way more of them. Exactly. And then on the flip side, operational teams are just feeling much more productive their day-to-day life is more enjoyable. They're using better tools. They're having to do less manual work.
And so, you know, it's almost trite in tech circles now, but the Javons paradox, you know, an asset becomes more productive. You don't want less. You want more. Yeah, exactly. And it is very much the case for us when it comes to engineers, you know, our engineers are just magnificently more productive. And so I mentioned earlier just making straight a platform for founders, like internal platform for founders, you know, going forward, you could say, well,
Because engineers are so productive, there will just be fewer engineers in the world. And I just really don't believe that. And that's not what we're seeing at all. You see that much more software creation. There was a narrative nine months ago about SaaS platforms and how they're vertical platforms, how they were all going to struggle. Our new SaaS platform cohort is 103% larger than in 2026 and it was in 2025.
So people are just saying, well, there are so many spaces that need a SaaS platform, I'm building it faster and faster and faster. And so I think there will be more software engineers in the world. We will need fewer of them to do the things we're already doing. And so Stripe then becomes, for new grads and early career engineers, more of an incubator of come in, figure out a high agency project that can help our users.
Let's get out of your way. Let's create the paved paths. Let's make it easy for you to go faster. And we should be able to just build more and more and more and not just random things, but adjacencies that compound what we're doing today. So spend management is adjacent to treasury.
and that might have been road mapped for two years from now. Instead, one engineer is picked it up as a project and they're just building it themselves. Actually, I wrote the first commit for it, but they're now running with it. They're more capable hands now. Exactly, more capable hands. So yeah, we believe the big opportunity and the one that we're leaning into is doing more with what we have and over time doing more with more. Yeah, I totally agree with that. And I wrote a piece recently
about founders being the asset class, like the representation of our market of late stage venture, which you guys are probably at the forefront of. Founders are the asset class because founders are going to be the ones who enable the companies to find the next product areas. And so this idea that you have to make trade-offs today around, do we try and build new products for revenue or cut costs? I think for companies like Stripe that are run by you guys, there's probably always going to be that next opportunity to create.
additional revenue opportunities, you know, find the new customer products that are a big hit and that is never going to go away. You're always going to have the chance to build more. Yes, absolutely. I do think it's a good moment for company leaders to create some resourcing back pressure because that back pressure drives more efficient and more expansive use of new tools. But I also imagine that in the years ahead we'll have a budgeting process that looks not that dissimilar for what has been in the past of
We're doing so much with what we have, we can do even more if we continue to expand resourcing. But in this moment, I think it is a good time to say, well, let's really do a lot with what we have today because you still see increases in productivity from what you already have. Beyond that, from a user's first standpoint, there's so much more they want from us. We've heard from a lot of users that for StripeTax, they want global filing.
And it took us a long time to get to, you know, US filing on Striptax, meaning that, you know, every state in the US will just automatically file 40. It's hard. It's a hard problem because you are dealing with so many different jurisdictions that accept filing in different ways. And so it took us a long time to get there. Global filing was the next ask. You know, we just don't want to have to think about this in any market. And we built
that in about a third of the time that it took us to get to US finally. And wow, with much greater complexity. Exactly, much greater complexity. And so it's just like an infinite list of asks and opportunities like that. And so if you're just relentlessly focused on users, you're going to focus on that. We launched recently a product called Stripe Treasury. And it's an interesting moment in sort of FinTech right now, because I think there is sort of an unbundling of what
banking means and Stripe is not a bank, does not aspire to be a bank, but does aspire to provide your banking portal and help you with global money movement. This is something that we've been asked for for a very long time. And so we built Stripe Treasury to allow our users to hold funds in dozens of currencies across many countries and just build what the banking portal should be able to do. And so we've focused on bringing
this experience to users extremely quickly. And what we're finding in every case is that the timelines that we thought were the best doable two years ago are now being compressed again and again and again. And it's because the direction that we're finding from an agentic engineering standpoint is kind of akin to
Injection molding, you know, it's a bit reductionist. Yeah. But when you look at sort of the growth of consumer packaged goods and toys and things like that, a lot of it just exploded post war. Yeah. And it was because we got really good in the 40s at melting plastic. You know, it's the injected injection molding screw that sort of, you know, melts plastic very evenly and sort of injects it into, you know, a metal casting. And that sort of...
how we're doing code production at this point. You know, creating the mold and the templates. You mentioned markdown files, like those are extremely, you need your agents files in every repo. And as long as you create those patterns and you sort of understand the pattern of how you integrate with financial institutions, you can hand off so much of the work to agents and they just get it done. And all of the time you end up spending is sort of on the back end at Coderview.
But even then, Asians are doing code reviews and better than humans do. So just again, compressing timelines, it just feels like a much bigger opportunity than optimizing cost structure. Yeah. I think you may be the first person to compare modern AI based software engineering to injection molding. So this is great. We're covering your guide. And I've actually been to an injection molding plant before. Yeah, yeah. That's pretty amazing. It's pretty amazing. Especially when you think about the fact that it was
probably 70 years ago that it was created. James Watson Hendry. I think it was the guy. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I've been in Pennsylvania. Yeah, there you go. Yeah, that's great. You know, if you, you know, as an investor in Stripe, and a large investor in Stripe, another way that I think about what you just described is the opportunity to optimize cost is finite, right? You said long versus short. Yeah, really like. Yeah, yeah, yeah. No, it's an optimization cost structure is going short.
sort of your own future potential and just building faster, building more is going long, you know, your future potential. It's like the capital allocation equivalent of like returning cash as opposed to reinvesting cash. Yes. Yeah. I got it. Okay. I want to shift over to a new topic, which you guys are on the cutting edge of and which gets a lot of play, but almost in like a nebulous sense. So I'd like to go a little bit deeper on it with you, which is sort of agents engaging in commerce on the internet.
What is the state of where we are today? What are the bottlenecks and how do you sort of view a framework for how that could be done in the future? Yeah. So we are, we talked about the Opus 4.5 Cambrian Explosion Moment. We haven't had that in agent to commerce today. There isn't a just there aren't a ton of canonical use cases you just see repeated over and over and over again. And there's a few reasons for that. One is we're missing primitives.
Right. Yeah. And just that's something we're very focused on. We created the tempo and machine payments protocol so that services can indicate what needs to be paid and how you can pay for it. So if you're selling an image or a piece of content online, you can request it and get a 402 response back. And it just says, like, here's how you buy me. So that's a primitive. We think machines will want to buy from
from other machines. And there's a question of like, what should checkout look like for agents? It's still sort of an open question. You know, browser automation is getting better, so maybe agents should just be crawling through checkout forms and tell them out. I think there's still a lot of open questions here. Yeah, that's the scumorphic version. Exactly. There's going to be a native version. Yeah. Yeah, I think that's right. I know that's right. So we're sort of at the missing primitives phase, and we're sort of figuring that out. And then there's a sociological phase of just
in what ways will agentic commerce be better than non-agentic commerce? And there's some very non-speculative ways in which it'll be better. Like just checkout pages shouldn't exist for humans, you know, with straight blink and shop-a-shop pay. It's very easy to get through a checkout page these days, but should you even need to go to one or should you just be able to say, buy it on a product display page?
I think so. I think just check our pages will go away. That'll be the best. Yeah, I think they'll go away. And so that's like a sort of non speculative but maybe less ambitious form of agent to commerce. I actually think that's interesting because you they will go away for human users too. Yes, this is not just like only I think that's go yes. Okay, so strike link like you have like 400 million users on this link and shop pay probably has some Yes, a couple of the large number and you can you can use those and just automate the whole process. Exactly. Yeah, we launched recently the link agent wallet so that there's now just a link CLI.
So an agent can just sweep up link credentials and go use them with humans in the loop to say how they can use them. I think one of the places we are the most excited about agentic commerce actually is B2B. So we launched straight projects. Straight projects is a way to scaffold apps. That's sort of the narrow definition of it.
But the most exciting thing that Start Projects is is a way to provision B2B services agentically. So you can go, an agent can go adopt it, versell for hosting and they can do it without you needing to go to versell.com and do anything. This is actually informed our investment thesis in a few investments recently. They're developer tools and we say, okay, assume that the agents are going to be the shoppers in the future. Exactly. Like is this the one that the agents will want to pick? Yes, exactly.
Exactly. And that's a very good framework. You know, an agent can go adopt Browserbase. And we actually had a really great demo a while back at Stripe where we used Browserbase live to, via an agent to fill out an NCAA bracket. Which I thought was awesome, because I have three brothers and, you know, we all love sports, but I'm always sort of too busy to engage in the family pools.
And so it was so cool to just watch the agent, you know, pick up a browser based session and, you know, fire up ESPN.com and do a bit of research and just like fill it out. How to do. I don't actually know. I don't think we ever sort of ran the evals on it, but I suspect probably as good as humans. It's probably better. Yeah, exactly. You're probably better. And so I do think agents sort of adopting B2B or sort of B2C services that are more utilitarian will be very popular. And so.
Today, again, as a primitive, we're just trying to make it easier for agents to adopt services. But I do think the sociology will continue to evolve. The long-running tasks are not sort of... I don't know that we've sort of figured out exactly how to do them on the consumer side. Yeah, it's not there yet. I was trying the other day, I was using a plug code.
to try to compose a song for my niece's birthday. Oh. Yeah, it was pretty cool. And, you know, in the past without a sooner, I just like definitely wouldn't have done that. With a sooner, I might do that. You might do it with the Higgs Guild as well. We're talking about them earlier. But I'm not sure that I want to go create a 1099 or 999 a month account with them. I just want the sort of micro consumption for that. And so, you know, along with the actual commerce primitives,
I think there's these micro consumption APIs that need to start to exist. And browser race we're talking about, they're sort of leaning into it. But I'm very bullish on all these services standing up, not necessarily anonymous, but just ephemeral or one time consumption. And I think that will really unlock agent at commerce too, because then you won't have to say, well, I need to pay these guys 10 bucks a month, but these guys 10 bucks a month. You just would say that. You get accounts and all this stuff. Exactly. You just use the service and pay. Agent, do this, discover the services. Your budget is $15.
My 10 year old has been creating rap songs, so I'm very familiar with all of these services. And by the way, the quality is actually pretty good, and he posts them on Spotify. But the execution maybe is not quite as good, but the lyrics are very good from AI, and the music itself is pretty good. So it's a... Yeah, I would welcome that. So the critical thing, I think, one of the critical things that you just said is...
this concept of micropayments or microtransactions. So this has been something that has been talked about probably since the advent of the internet as an opportunity. Like why do you think now it could work? Well agents really increase human agency I guess it almost sounds redundant. But you know talking about these applications composing a song for your knees, filling out your NCAA bracket, whatever else.
It's really hard to do without agents to take a lot of time. You're creating all these different accounts. And so I'm just very bullish on services leaning into saying you can use me ephemerally, you can use me in a very sort of lightweight way. And I think to make that work, you're just going to need to support microtransactions. I think the case against microtransactions has
always been well, you're trying to consume content and if you're trying to sell an article, you're always going to be squeezed between the subscriber business model and the free business model. Yeah, like you want to capture the excess as part of the subscriber. Exactly, you capture the excess or you do that and just like they're one or the other is better than what you're doing. And I think that was probably true in the past, but as you give agents more complex tasks,
You know, you want them to be these little sort of hummingbirds, like going around the internet, just surfing up a little data here, you know, pulling it over here, you know, some very transient ephemeral storage, doing a little compute over here. And you don't want the individual human to have to think about what they're using. You want them to think about what they're using in that these services are secure, right? Right there. Of course. They're bona fide, but you don't want them to have to sort of create accounts everywhere. So I think microtransactions will just be necessary for that.
economy to exist, the sort of agent economy. And then the flip side, they're now eminently possible because of stable coins. And stable coins are today relatively unergonomic. So if you're a human, you have to go jump through a bunch of hoops. But if you just give an agent a budget, they can easily take dollars, move into stables, or just use a shared, a stored balance.
and find a way to check out and they don't mind the sort of back and forth. Yeah, I totally agree with that. And look, we've seen that transition that's happened in a lot of software business models today, right? Like the predominant business model of selling subscriptions and seeds, and we've now seen a shift to consumption and I think
There's probably analogies where the consumers are better off because they can get access to more stuff and then the businesses can access more people which they otherwise couldn't access for a certain service. So my hope is that that does come into play. So on the topic of stablecoins, so we've covered sort of how you guys build software, how you move so fast in an AI development world. We've talked about the idea of commerce, agent to commerce.
Talk about stablecoins. Like you said, there's a lot of friction in the process today, but just state of the stablecoin market and what you see the opportunity to be for the next call of five years. So I'm an infrastructure nerd, so I always will go there first. And stablecoins are just a better platform for moving money than exists otherwise. I strongly agree. And better for a couple of reasons. There are certain countries that have rolled out really good payment systems, most of them are nationalized.
UPI in India. Actually, it's interesting when you look at these economies, the percentage of sub $5 payments in India I believe is on UPI is I think something like 86%, whereas in the US, I think it's single digits percent. So, you know, there's some good, cheap, fast payment schemes that are nationalized, PIX another one in Brazil, which is brilliant, Medi-Arcly.
But you need a shelling point for the global economy, right? Right. Just what can we all agree on? And that's where crypto rails solve this political problem. Right. Just this platform works everywhere. And so if we just all used it, the world, the global financial system would work better, it'd be faster, it'd be cheaper and so on. So if we all went to sleep tonight and woke up tomorrow and we all held stables, it would just be a better global fund. Less friction and less cost. Exactly. In the economy. Exactly.
Now that might be one of those should work this way may never, you know work this way problems and so we are sort of resolutely focused on trying to change that. We talked earlier about Stripe Treasury and you know we decided to make stable points native to Stripe Treasury. So you can just hold a balance in stables just like you hold a balance in USD or UR or QBP or anything like that. So we believe that the opportunity for stables is just
faster money movement, cheaper money movement and more global money movement. Right now you can be a Stripe user in a camera with the exact number is but around 60 countries in fiat, but you can be a Stripe user in stablecoins in I think about 150 countries. So just bringing more people into the online economy in a way that allows them to
you know, transact with, you know, the AI companies and, you know, as the economy, the software economy gets more and more global, bringing more people into it is more and more valuable. You can build a powerful AI company with two engineers in Thailand, just as well as you can do it in the US or as well as you can do it in Brazil. So, you know, for Sables, for us, it is higher performance, more global. Yeah. And I like the position that you guys are in as a relationship stablecoins, just because, again, talk about meeting the market where it is.
like people don't want to cut over full wholesale and just drop all their fiat and move over to stablecoin. So I think the relationships that you have and the sort of comprehensive offering that you have allows for adoption to happen at the pace that the enterprises want adoption to adopt at, or startups. Yeah. Yeah. And all of this works. You know, when you really lean into it, Felix Bogar, Felix, I think is, is, is, is called now, which started as a remittance company between the US and
and Mexico and now has other corridors as well. They built it on stables and a few years in, they're now between 5 and 10% of remittances along that corridor, which is the largest remittance corridor in the world. And so, you think about how long it takes companies to move fiat money.
efficiently, you know, how long it took initially for the wise of the world to do this, let alone the Western unions before it. And, you know, these are great companies, but to get to 5 to 10% in just a few years is amazing. That's remarkable. Yeah. I'd love to have you talk a little bit about tempo. Yeah. So, you know, obviously it's a big important project that you guys are in the center of. Talk about, you know, where that is and what the aspirations for it are. Yeah. I think this, I'll just
play the infrastructure nerd card again for a second. There are great blockchains and I think there was no obvious need for another blockchain outside of payments. And there's a whole lot of reasons why a payment specific blockchain can work really well.
Privacy for one, because blockchains are generally public and sort of reverse engineer what's happening on blockchains. So I want to make sure that privacy is a first class primitive. Making sure that throughput is never sacrificed. Blockchains are disproportionately used for trading.
And so when you see massive trading events happen, you'll typically see performance degrade a lot transaction fees. Like finding a way to create a blockchain where the transaction fee is never going to spike because other blockchains have... Availability is important. Exactly. And they have floating sort of gas fees. And so the project there is just saying how do we move money as efficiently, consistently and cheaply as possible?
Still in the early stages of building out getting a lot of great traction you were working with companies like Door dash, you know making it sort of the default but not only blockchain in Stripe and feeling very optimistic about that's great. That's awesome Last topic I would love to cover with you is just the sort of token economy And so you know it sounds a little buzzwordy, but you guys are you know, I think over two trillion of volume now
And I think you and I would probably share the belief that the token economy is going to be one of the biggest things we've ever seen. So what do you think is kind of the state of play for accessing tokens? Obviously, there's a lot of work that gets done in first party applications today. But what do you think is sort of the future state of how we all access models and tokens? Well, I've always loved the word token. And the reason is that it just sounds like an approximation of money.
Yeah, and increasing that's just what it is right. We're seeing you know, we talked earlier about you know, free trial abuse multi-accounting and The attacks that we're seeing against users who have sort of general whose platforms are general purpose token consumers You know, you can do just about anything with tokens on cursor, right? You just want anything with tokens on on replete
So the attacks against these users are very sophisticated. They're very reminiscent of what we see in terms of people trying to steal money from stripe users. And so there's this blurring that you see between tokens and dollars. And so for us, we think about wanting to help users move money, store money, send money safely, compliant, and so on.
We now feel this mandate to do the same thing on tokens, right? To protect our users in the same way. And, you know, over time, I think this is only going to happen more, right? You know, we talk about some of these long running agent tasks, and a lot of them will replace, you know, services. You'll just be able to say, you know, close my books. And I used to pay, you know, a human in tokens for that. Now I, or many humans now I pay.
fewer humans or a human or sorry, endowers should have that now. Okay, fewer humans or a human. And tokens. End tokens, right? Because they're augmented by agents. So we just want to make sure that moving between tokens and dollars is as seamless as moving and safe as moving between dollars and euros. We're at the beginning of this journey, but we think it's going to be a big part of the future of Stripe. Yeah, that's awesome. Yeah, it's super exciting and it looks...
Personally speaking, I think you guys have a real right to play a role there because of the relationship that you have with somebody. Yes. Somebody helped me since inception all the way through down as I see you said. Yeah, and we usually, it's funny, we're always a little bit careful internally about talking about rights and so we talk about mandates. And yeah, we feel like we have a mandate to help users with this and
And so that's why we're really leaning into it. We're also focusing even more on spend management for our customers. They're using Stripe Treasury, they're thinking a lot about how much they're spending and how to reduce their spending, how their spending ties to the revenue. And a lot of token usage is actually in product. So you see sort of two different types of token usage. One is to build things, this is sort of the OPEX management side of.
of token management and then there's the product efficacy side right of token management just how good is my token oriented or sort of token driven product you know how should I shift between different models to make it the most effective and So we're really thinking about how do we help users on both of these? Yeah for sure. I mean certainly in the latter this sort of you know
Position as an orchestration layer as it helps you effectively get the most out of tokens and yes, you know also maintain some form of control I think is like never been more top of mind than it is right now. Yes, absolutely Yeah, and it's interesting because there's a hypothesis that you know software will be severely commoditized And it's plausible, you know, I think we're we're at the let's say we're
either in the singularity or creeping towards the singularity and it's very hard to estimate what a feature looks like where models are recursively generating models and so on and so on. But we are seeing the exact opposite right now where software creation is exploding. Yes, customers are monetizing.
faster than ever and we talked about our 2026 cohorts growing 50% faster than our or 50% larger and growing faster than 25 cohort that one being 70% larger and growing faster than the 24 cohort and So you know some more software being created it's being adopted faster than ever before and then more straight products are being adopted than ever before and 11 labs is using
14 straight products. I wish it were 11 in a way, but actually I'm glad it's 14. Just make it 22. Yeah, yeah, yeah, 22. We're close with Matty and he does everything in denominations of 11. Exactly. He's got a shoot for 22. Exactly. And you know, there's a lot more to software than just building, right? There's the expertise about how abstractions should thread through your entire business.
and sort of keeping those up to date. And you have turnover inside of your company. And so you build a system internally and then it starts to sort of degrade and that person leaves the company and the expertise goes away. And so we think about just how can we help companies across their entire revenue stack, manage cash, manage revenue, close the books faster, grow faster, globalize faster. And that opportunity I think is just larger than it was ever, ever was before. Yeah, couldn't agree more.
So in closing, I wanted to just get your take and this is, I don't want to get too deep into, you know, the role of humans versus AI. But one of the things that Stripe has always been universally recognized for and appreciated for, I think is your taste, right? And it sounds funny because you're an infrastructure company, but I think it's generally agreed upon. How do you continue to uphold that at such a large scale and with so much of the work that you're doing now being done by AI?
Yeah, it's interesting how much the word taste is being used right now. It's sort of hard sometimes, you know, the cynical view is that it's
how we're all justifying our future value. Yeah, that no one actually has taste and it's just we're all reproducing machines of things that we had previously perceived. Yes. And like my fingers are no longer as useful, but this nebulous notion of taste is and models will never have taste and so on. It's probably just not true. Yeah, I agree with you on that. But to your more proximate to your question, you know, product quality is really
really core to our culture and to our identity and It's for a few reasons like one is just we want users to have amazing tools that are carefully crafted that you know can make their make them go faster, you know enjoy You know the the the journey of building a company that much more, you know, it's not an easy journey, but if you have you know
tools that are surprisingly great, it feels that much better. So it's a big user lens. Another dimension of it is it's just more fun. You look at what you created with your team and you're like, wow, that looks amazing versus you kind of janked this thing together and it barely works. And it just isn't as fun to go through the slog, the long nights, the long weekends and so on to build it.
I think the single thing I would say for scaling tastes, it's right. Well, actually two things. One is I think it has to be a top stat. You just have to say it over and over and over again. It's like the company strategy of when the start someone them again. It's like talk about quality and talk about it again. And then the other thing is just use the product. Yes. And make it easy to use the product. You know, in aviation, you know, simulation is so important like you can't
You can't just say like, I hope the jet works. You have to kind of prove to yourself that it does before you ever fly it or an NVIDIA, you know, they really hit escape velocity was when they, you know, went from needing to wait for the fab to give them the chips to try the chips to actually simulate chip problems. And so we actually invest a lot in simulating the usage of products. Yeah, well, and so you can point to an account and say, you know, give me something that looks like that. Yeah, but make it, you know, completely PII.
you know, free, you know, randomized the growth rates so I don't actually know how big they are, but just...
you know, the day-to-day problems that they face, you know, the ups and downs of their business, the seasonality, you know, give me a sense of that and then, you know, make it feel alive, you know, make it so that I'm feeling like I'm receiving disputes from customers and refunds are happening. And of course, these aren't real disputes. They're not real refunds, but just give me the experience that users having so I can really live in it and use that with my team. And so I think, you know, you have the mandate to use the product and we really
Ask our EM's to lead this because they're the ones who control the resources and they're the ones who can sort of say wow This does not feel good. It needs to get fixed. So we're gonna you know Our next sprint is gonna be elevated quality and the other side It's how do you give people the tools to do it more easily? So scaling tastes for us is you know culture and it is the You know shibboleths and then it is the daily rhythm. So just using the products and stepping into these issues. That's awesome. That's so great Will
This is so fun to talk to you about all these topics, obviously covering how you're building so much product inside Stripe, which is super unique and right on the cutting edge, I think, and the future of how we engage an agent of commerce and stable coins. One of the things that I think you guys have said is, how do we assure that we build the next Stripe inside of Stripe? And I love that in closing and I really appreciate the time. Yeah, thank you. Great to be here.
Thanks for listening to this episode of the A16Z podcast. If you liked this episode, be sure to like, comment, subscribe, leave us a rating or review, and share it with your friends and family. For more episodes, go to YouTube, Apple Podcasts, and Spotify. Follow us on X and A16Z, and subscribe to our substack at a16z.substack.com. Thanks again for listening, and I'll see you in the next episode. As a reminder, the content here is for informational purposes only.
should not be taken as legal business, tax, or investment advice, or be used to evaluate any investment or security, and is not directed at any investors or potential investors in any A16Z fund. Please note that A16Z and its affiliates may also maintain investments in the companies discussed in this podcast. For more details, including a link to our investments, please see a16z.com forward slash disclosures.